Guide to the Who Needs Feminism Records, 2012-ongoing UA.31.08.0009
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Who Needs Feminism Records
2012-ongoing
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Who Needs Feminism (Project)
UA.31.08.0009
0.25 Linear Feet
Who Needs Feminism started as a class project for Women in the Public Sphere: History, Theory, and Practice in Spring 2012. The project began a campaign of posters and photographs on social media depicting people of varying gender and ethnicity holding white board signs with the text "I need feminism because ...". The Who Needs Feminism records include captures of the campaign's Tumblr and Facebook pages, print-outs of social media campaign activity, news articles on the campaign, and reflection essays written by the 16 students who originally created the campaign.
Biographical / Historical
Who Needs Feminism started as a class project for Women in the Public Sphere: History, Theory, and Practice in Spring 2012. The class, taught by Dr. Rachel Seidman and made up of sixteen women students, began a campaign with posters around campus and photographs on social media depicting people of varying gender and ethnicity holding white board signs with the text "I need feminism because ..." and describing different reasons for supporting feminism, with the text WHO NEEDS FEMINISM across the top. Posters were hung around campus and the students wrote an editorial for the Chronicle on April 12, 2012 (http://www.dukechronicle.com/article/2012/04/who-needs-feminism). The campaign also included pages on Facebook and Tumblr, which allowed members of the Duke community and the public to post their own pictures and comments.
The campaign was designed to draw attention to misconceptions about feminism and who is a feminist as well as to promote discussion about the importance of feminism in everyday life. The campaign's pages on Facebook and Tumblr quickly acquired thousands of views, likes, and posts; by May 9, 2012, whoneedsfeminism.tumblr.com had received more than 91,000 visits. As of November 2016, the Facebook page (www.facebook.com/WhoNeedsFeminism) had more than 39,000 likes, and the Tumblr account had more than 4,500 posts. The campaign also spread to other colleges and universities as well as groups and organizations around the world, and the Duke group created a start-up guide to support these efforts.
The campaign also generated negative reactions, including vandalizing or tearing down the original posters on campus and widespread backlash via social media comments and submissions. A campaign called Women Against Feminism used the original campaign's structure of individuals holding up signs stating "I don't need feminism ..."
Access Restrictions
In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Who Needs Feminism Records were received by the University Archives as a gift in 2012 and as regular web captures 2012-ongoing.
Related Materials
Women's initiative, Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Women's Studies Program Records, Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Campus Culture Initiative Records, Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
"Who Needs Feminism?", The Chronicle, April 12, 2012.
Collection Overview
The Who Needs Feminism records include website snapshots of the campaign Tumblr and Facebook pages, print-outs of social media campaign activity, news articles on the campaign, and reflection essays written by the 16 students who originally created the campaign. Website captures include daily snapshots of the Facebook and Tumblr pages from 2012-2016. Print-outs include posts and submissions on the campaign's Tumblr and Facebook pages, as well as posts on Twitter including the hashtag #whoneedsfeminism and articles written about the campaign at Duke and elsewhere. Also included are some limited statistics from Google Analytics on the Tumblr page in April and early May 2012.
Reflection essays written by the 16 students in Women in the Public Sphere include the students' thoughts on the origin and development of the campaign as well as reactions to what happened as the campaign gained worldwide attention. Several of these essays have not been released for access by their authors and may not be viewed.
Feminism -- North Carolina; Feminists -- North Carolina; Women college students; Internet and activism -- North Carolina; Social media -- North Carolina; User-generated content -- North Carolina; Duke University -- Students; Seidman, Rachel Filene; Who Needs Feminism (Project); Tumblr (Electronic resource); Facebook (Electronic resource)
- Women in the Public Sphere Class Materials, April-May 2012
  Scope and Contents
  Materials in this series were gathered or created as part of the Women in the Public Sphere class project, Who Needs Feminism. Included are several folders of printed out content from the Tumblr and Facebook pages, Twitter posts using the #whoneedsfeminism hastag, and news articles both on campus and from the Internet in general. Also included are reflection essays written by the students in the class on the project and its impact.
  - Tumblr, April 2012 (Box 1)
  - Facebook, April 2012 (Box 1)
  - Twitter, April 2012 (Box 1)
  - Internet Articles, April 2012 (Box 1)
  - Campus Media, April 2012 (Box 1)
  - Analytics, April-May 2012 (Box 1)
  - Reflections on Who Needs Feminism, Women in the Public Sphere, April 2012 (Box 1)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Permission has been granted for researcher access.
  - Reflections on Who Needs Feminism, Women in the Public Sphere, April 2012 (Box 1)
    Permission has NOT been granted for researcher access.
- Web Archives, 2012-ongoing
  Materials in this series included web captures of the Tumblr and Facebook pages of the project. As of 2016, only the Facebook page was still active.
  - Who Needs Feminism Tumblr page, 2012-2015
  - Who Needs Feminism Tumblr RSS feed, 2012-2015
  - Who Needs Feminism Facebook page, 2012-ongoing